<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Researches | Mario Ivan Jaen / Homepage</title>
    <link>https://mjaenm.github.io/research/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mjaenm.github.io/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Researches</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mjaenm.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Researches</title>
      <link>https://mjaenm.github.io/research/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>R&amp;D applications in quantitative finance, trading and financial markets</title>
      <link>https://mjaenm.github.io/research/finance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mjaenm.github.io/research/finance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tackled a ​portfolio compression problem, which consisted of: given a fixed set of deals with a specific sensitivity (delta) value, to find the smallest basket of deals with the same delta from a big pool of internal live trades. The external version of this problem (trades agreed between a network of banks) was solved using a vendor solution (TriOptima). Under our own initiative we modeled this problem and it turned out that it resembles the ​subset-sum problem family, which is known to be NP-complete. We applied a tailored optimization method found in the computational finance literature to get an approximate solution&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental research in Information Geometry Optimization and Estimation of Distribution Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://mjaenm.github.io/research/optimization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mjaenm.github.io/research/optimization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with ​Prof. Arturo Hernandez and Prof. John McCall in black-box optimization methods. I analyzed population based algorithms that employ probabilistic models to guide the search process and that are built upon the Information
Geometry (IG) framework. Our goal was to introduce a novel global optimization algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-output&#34;&gt;Research output:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research stay in the Computational Intelligence Group at Robert Gordon University, UK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graduated of the CIMAT CS MS program with the thesis &lt;a href=&#34;https://cimat.repositorioinstitucional.mx/jspui/handle/1008/484&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A Univariate Boltzmann based Estimation of Distribution Algorithm Using the Natural
Gradient for Updating the Parameters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research in Metaheuristic Optimization and Particle Filtering methods; applications in computational chemistry and computer vision</title>
      <link>https://mjaenm.github.io/research/particlefiltering/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mjaenm.github.io/research/particlefiltering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my honors thesis I studied the main principles behind evolutionary algorithms and in particular, metaheuristics such as Particle Swarm Optimization. The purpose of this research was to develop hybrid approaches together with the particle filter method (PF) applied to the video object tracking problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We developed a color-based observation model and a linear transition model to use it in the canonical PF. Then a dynamic optimization step was combined with the PF to enhance the state estimation over time. Our appoach showed competitive performance w.r.t particle filters on complex benchmarks used in literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vh-52Q7FtCA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6fkjifJtDgU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-outputs&#34;&gt;Research outputs:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mario Ivan Jaen, Arturo Hernandez, Rafael Rivera, 
“Seguimiento de objetos basado en algoritmos de optimizacion bioinspirados”, 
Talk at XXIV Escuela Nacional de Optimizacion y Analisis Numerico, (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.smcca.org.mx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ENOAN 2014&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awarded the best undergraduate thesis in computer science nationwide by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aniei.org.mx/ANIEI/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ANIEI, Mexico&lt;/a&gt; 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awarded honorable mention on final oral defense, Veracruz, Mexico 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;application-to-computational-chemistry&#34;&gt;Application to computational chemistry&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary-1&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my senior year as an undergrad student at Tecnologico Nacional de Mexico-Veracruz I did research in combinatorial optimization. The goal was to tackle the chemical equation balancing problem by using exact and metaheuristic methods. I contributed by implementing algebraic methods based on matrix computations and metaheuristics using object-oriented-programming in Java. We collected a dataset for testing this problem and presented the experimental results in a local conference on optimization and software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-outputs-1&#34;&gt;Research outputs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk at &lt;a href=&#34;http://campusv.uaem.mx/cicos/01.anteriores/cicos2014/cicos2014.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Congreso Internacional de Computo en Optimizacion y Software&lt;/a&gt; (CICos 2014).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Palos-Sanchez, Leticia, Jaen-Marquez, Mario, Rivera-Lopez, Rafael, “&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.progmat.uaem.mx:8080/Vol7num3/vol7num3art7.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Modelado Orientado a Objetos del Problema de Balanceo de Ecuaciones Quimicas y su Resolucion utilizando Metodos Algebraicos”, Programacion Matematica y Software&lt;/a&gt;, Vol. 7, pp. 52-63, 2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
